<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ipums-ddi-xslt.xsl"?>
<codeBook xmlns="ddi:codebook:2_5" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="ddi:codebook:2_5 http://www.ddialliance.org/Specification/DDI-Codebook/2.5/XMLSchema/codebook.xsd" version="2.5" ID="ddi2-145656_cps_00002.dat-cps.ipums.org">
  <docDscr>
    <citation>
      <titlStmt>
        <titl>Codebook for an IPUMS-CPS Data Extract</titl>
        <subTitl>DDI 2.5 metadata describing the extract file  'cps_00002.dat'</subTitl>
        <IDNo>ddi2-145656_cps_00002.dat-cps.ipums.org</IDNo>
      </titlStmt>
      <rspStmt>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="University of Minnesota">Minnesota Population Center</AuthEnty>
      </rspStmt>
      <prodStmt>
        <producer abbr="MPC" affiliation="University of Minnesota" role="Documentation">Minnesota Population Center</producer>
        <prodDate date="2020-03-09">March 9, 2020</prodDate>
        <prodPlac>Minnesota Population Center, 50 Willey Hall, 225 - 19th Avenue South, Minneapolis, MN 55455</prodPlac>
      </prodStmt>
      <distStmt>
        <contact affiliation="University of Minnesota" URI="http://pop.umn.edu">Minnesota Population Center</contact>
      </distStmt>
    </citation>
  </docDscr>
  <stdyDscr>
    <citation>
      <titlStmt>
        <titl>User Extract cps_00002.dat</titl>
      </titlStmt>
      <rspStmt>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="University of Minnesota">Minnesota Population Center</AuthEnty>
      </rspStmt>
      <prodStmt>
        <producer abbr="MPC" affiliation="University of Minnesota" role="Documentation">Minnesota Population Center</producer>
        <prodDate date="2020-03-09">March 9, 2020</prodDate>
        <prodPlac>Minnesota Population Center, 50 Willey Hall, 225 - 19th Avenue South, Minneapolis, MN 55455</prodPlac>
      </prodStmt>
      <distStmt>
        <contact affiliation="University of Minnesota" URI="http://pop.umn.edu">Minnesota Population Center</contact>
      </distStmt>
      <serStmt>
        <serName abbr="cps">IPUMS-CPS</serName>
        <serInfo>DOI:10.18128/D030.V7.0</serInfo>
      </serStmt>
      <verStmt>
        <version date="2020-03-09"/>
      </verStmt>
    </citation>
    <stdyInfo>
      <subject>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Linking Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Economic Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Linking Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Demographics Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Ethnicity/Nativity Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Education Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
      </subject>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-2955">
        <timePrd event="single" date="2019-01">2019-01</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-2956">
        <timePrd event="single" date="2019-02">2019-02</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-2963">
        <timePrd event="single" date="2019-03">2019-03</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-2957">
        <timePrd event="single" date="2019-03">2019-03</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-2958">
        <timePrd event="single" date="2019-04">2019-04</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-2959">
        <timePrd event="single" date="2019-05">2019-05</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-2961">
        <timePrd event="single" date="2019-06">2019-06</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-2962">
        <timePrd event="single" date="2019-07">2019-07</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-2964">
        <timePrd event="single" date="2019-08">2019-08</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-2965">
        <timePrd event="single" date="2019-09">2019-09</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-2966">
        <timePrd event="single" date="2019-10">2019-10</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-2967">
        <timePrd event="single" date="2019-11">2019-11</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-2968">
        <timePrd event="single" date="2019-12">2019-12</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, January 2019; regular size
]]></notes>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, February 2019; regular size
]]></notes>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, ASEC 2019; regular size
]]></notes>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, March 2019; regular size
]]></notes>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, April 2019; regular size
]]></notes>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, May 2019; regular size
]]></notes>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, June 2019; regular size
]]></notes>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, July 2019; regular size
]]></notes>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, August 2019; regular size
]]></notes>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, September 2019; regular size
]]></notes>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, October 2019; regular size
]]></notes>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, November 2019; regular size
]]></notes>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, December 2019; regular size
]]></notes>
    </stdyInfo>
    <dataAccs>
      <useStmt>
        <confDec required="no"><![CDATA[None]]></confDec>
        <contact affiliation="Minnesota Population Center" URI="http://cps.ipums.org/">IPUMS-CPS</contact>
        <citReq><![CDATA[Publications and research reports based on the IPUMS-CPS database must cite it appropriately. The citation should include the following:

Sarah Flood,  Miriam King,  Renae Rodgers,  Steven Ruggles and J. Robert Warren. Integrated Public Use Microdata Series, Current Population Survey: Version 7.0 [dataset]. Minneapolis, MN: IPUMS, 2019. https://doi.org/10.18128/D030.V7.0

The licensing agreement for use of IPUMS-CPS data requires that users supply us with the title and full citation for any publications, research reports, or educational materials making use of the data or documentation. Please add your citation to the IPUMS bibliography: http://bibliography.ipums.org/]]></citReq>
        <conditions><![CDATA[Users of IPUMS-CPS data must agree to abide by the conditions of use. A user's license is valid for one year and may be renewed.  Users must agree to the following conditions:

(1) No fees may be charged for use or distribution of the data.  All persons are granted a limited license to use these data, but you may not charge a fee for the data if you distribute it to others.

(2) Cite IPUMS appropriately.  For information on proper citation,  refer to the citation requirement section of this DDI document.

(3) Tell us about any work you do using the IPUMS.  Publications, research  reports, or presentations making use of IPUMS-CPS should be added to our  Bibliography. Continued funding for the IPUMS depends on our ability to  show our sponsor agencies that researchers are using the data for productive  purposes.

(4) Use it for GOOD -- never for EVIL.]]></conditions>
        <disclaimer>The user of the data acknowledges that the original collector of the data, the authorized distributor of the data, and the relevant funding agency bear no responsibility for use of the data or for interpretations or inferences based upon such uses.</disclaimer>
      </useStmt>
    </dataAccs>
    <notes><![CDATA[User-provided description:  Extracto de primeras variables de interés]]></notes>
  </stdyDscr>
  <fileDscr ID="ExtractData">
    <fileTxt>
      <fileName>cps_00002.dat</fileName>
      <fileCont>Microdata records</fileCont>
      <fileStrc type="rectangular">
      </fileStrc>
      <fileType charset="ISO-8859-1">ISO-8859-1 data file</fileType>
      <format>fixed length fields</format>
      <filePlac>Minnesota Population Center, 50 Willey Hall, 225 - 19th Avenue South, Minneapolis, MN 55455</filePlac>
    </fileTxt>
  </fileDscr>
  <dataDscr>
    <var ID="YEAR" files="ExtractData" name="YEAR" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="1" width="4" EndPos="4"/>
      <labl>Survey year</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[YEAR reports the year in which the survey was conducted.  YEARP is repeated on person records.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
YEAR is a 4-digit numeric value.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="SERIAL" files="ExtractData" name="SERIAL" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="5" width="5" EndPos="9"/>
      <labl>Household serial number</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[SERIAL is an identifying number unique to each household in a given survey month and year.  All person records are assigned the same serial number as the household record they follow.  A combination of YEAR, MONTH, and SERIAL provides a within-sample unique identifier for every household in IPUMS-CPS; YEAR, SERIAL, and PERNUM uniquely identify every person in the database within sample.

SERIAL is a new value generated for IPUMS-CPS and should not be confused with the household serial number created by the Census Bureau and included in the original CPS data.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
SERIAL is a 5-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="MONTH" files="ExtractData" name="MONTH" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="10" width="2" EndPos="11"/>
      <labl>Month</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[MONTH indicates the calendar month of the CPS interview.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>01</catValu>
        <labl>January</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>02</catValu>
        <labl>February</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>03</catValu>
        <labl>March</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>04</catValu>
        <labl>April</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>05</catValu>
        <labl>May</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>06</catValu>
        <labl>June</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>07</catValu>
        <labl>July</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>08</catValu>
        <labl>August</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>09</catValu>
        <labl>September</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>10</catValu>
        <labl>October</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>11</catValu>
        <labl>November</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>12</catValu>
        <labl>December</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="HWTFINL" files="ExtractData" name="HWTFINL" intrvl="contin" dcml="4">
      <location StartPos="12" width="10" EndPos="21"/>
      <labl>Household weight, Basic Monthly</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[HWTFINL is a household-level weight that should be used to generate statistics about households. The CPS uses a complex stratified sampling scheme, and HWTFINL must be used to produce unbiased household-level statistics from IPUMS-CPS basic monthly samples. For analyses of March Annual Social and Economic (ASEC) data, researchers should use HWTSUPP. For individual-level analyses, researchers should use WTFINL, WTSUPP, or EARNWT. 

HWTFINL generally has the same value as WTFINL for the household head or reference person. Vacant housing units and households that could not be interviewed due to residents' absence or refusal to participate have a value of zero in HWTFINL; such sampled units were included in the public use CPS data beginning in 1988.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
HWTFINL is a 10-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="CPSID" files="ExtractData" name="CPSID" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="22" width="14" EndPos="35"/>
      <labl>CPSID, household record</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[CPSID is an IPUMS-CPS defined variable that uniquely identifies households across CPS samples. The first six digits of CPSID index the four-digit year and two-digit month that the household was first in the CPS. CPSID allows users to link a household record across samples, based on the 4-8-4 rotation pattern, by assigning a unique CPSID value based on a combination of household identifiers. CPSID will only ever appear for a maximum of 8 times, which is the number of times a household may be observed in the CPS survey (as indexed by MIS). In some cases, a household will appear fewer than 8 times due to migration, mortality, non-response, and recording errors. CPSID Extensive documentation about the creation of CPSID is available elsewhere [URL omitted from DDI.].

CPSID may also be used to link ASEC respondents who are in the March Basic Monthly file to other months of CPS data. This linking is made possible by IPUMS through the creation of MARBASECIDP. Users should note that ASEC oversample households (as indicated by ASECOVERH) will always have a CPSID value of 0.

Users may also want to see CPSIDP for more information about linking individuals across time using a person-specific version of CPSID.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
CPSID is a 14-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Linking Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="ASECFLAG" files="ExtractData" name="ASECFLAG" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="36" width="1" EndPos="36"/>
      <labl>Flag for ASEC</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[ASECFLAG indicates whether the respondent is part of the ASEC or the March Basic. This variable is useful for users who wish to distinguish ASEC and March Basic files in their extracts. See further information [URL omitted from DDI.] about the ASEC versus the March Basic Monthly Files.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>1</catValu>
        <labl>ASEC</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>2</catValu>
        <labl>March Basic</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="ASECWTH" files="ExtractData" name="ASECWTH" intrvl="contin" dcml="4">
      <location StartPos="37" width="10" EndPos="46"/>
      <labl>Annual Social and Economic Supplement Household weight</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[ASECWTH is a household-level weight that should be used to generate statistics about households in March Annual Social and Economic (ASEC) Supplement data. The CPS uses a complex stratified sampling scheme, and ASECWTH must be used to produce unbiased household-level statistics from the IPUMS-CPS ASEC data. For analyses of non-ASEC data, researchers should use HWTFINL. For individual-level analyses, researchers should use WTFINL,  ASECWT, or EARNWT. 

ASECWTH generally has the same value as WTSUPP for the household head or reference person. Vacant housing units and households that could not be interviewed due to residents' absence or refusal to participate have a value of zero in HWTSUPP; such sampled units were included in the public use CPS data beginning in 1988. 

Estimates on the entire population are prepared by projecting forward the resident population from the last available census. These projections are derived by updating the demographic census data from a number of other data sources that account for death, births and net migration. About 3 years after every census (i.e. 2003 for the 2000 Census and 2013 for the 2010 Census), the Census Bureau updates its independent population control and provides a new weight for the relevant years.

Two important points should be noted here. First, the lag between when the Census is conducted and when the CPS weights are updated is about 3 years. While the Census data are being processed, the CPS files are made available using the weighting scheme from the US Census prior to the latest Census. Second, once the files are updated, the old weights become obsolete and are replaced in the IPUMS data extract system. Published estimates from the lag years that use the old weights are not always updated. For example, 2010 poverty estimates were released in ASEC using the 2000 population controls. Once the 2010 population controls were made available, IPUMS-CPS replaced the ASEC 2010, 2011, and 2012 weights that are based on the 2000 population control with weights that are based on the 2010 population controls.

IPUMS-CPS makes available only the most up-to-date weights. The old values are available here: Old SPM and Weights Values [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
ASECWTH is a 10-digit numeric variable with four implied decimals.  That is, 1234567890 should be interpreted as 123456.7890.  The IPUMS command files automatically divide ASECWTH by 10,000, so no further adjustment is needed.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="HHINCOME" files="ExtractData" name="HHINCOME" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="47" width="8" EndPos="54"/>
      <labl>Total household income</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[HHINCOME reports the total money income during the previous calendar year of all adult household members.  The amount should equal the sum of all household members' individual incomes as recorded in the IPUMS-CPS variable INCTOT.  The persons included were those present in the household at the time of the survey.  People who lived in the household during the previous year but were not still living there at the time of the survey are not included; household members who lived elsewhere during the previous year but had joined the household at the time of the survey are included.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
99999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).


		
1968-1975: -9999997 (Loss of $9999 or more dollars).

See User Note [URL omitted from DDI.] for these codes]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Economic Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="FAMINC" files="ExtractData" name="FAMINC" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="55" width="3" EndPos="57"/>
      <labl>Family income of householder</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[FAMINC reports annual family income, in categories, of all persons related to the head of household/householder. For individuals who are not part of the householder's family, FAMINC reports the value for the householder's family. 

This measure includes the income of all members of the household who are 15 years of age or older.  Income includes money from jobs; net income from business, farm or rent; pensions; dividends; interest; Social Security payments; and any other monetary income received by family members.

Family income is collected as part of the basic monthly survey. At the end of the monthly labor force survey, respondents are asked to choose the category that represents the total combined income during the past 12 months for all members of the householder's family. The questionnaire says that "This includes money from jobs, net income from business, farm or rent, pensions, dividends, interest, social security payments and any other money income received" by members of the householder's family who are 15 years of age or older. Available categories change over time.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>100</catValu>
        <labl>Under $5,000</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>110</catValu>
        <labl>Under $1,000</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>111</catValu>
        <labl>Under $500</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>112</catValu>
        <labl>$500 - 999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>120</catValu>
        <labl>$1,000 - 1,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>121</catValu>
        <labl>$1,000 - 1,499</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>122</catValu>
        <labl>$1,500-1,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>130</catValu>
        <labl>$2,000 - 2,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>131</catValu>
        <labl>$2,000 - 2,499</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>132</catValu>
        <labl>$2,500 - 2,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>140</catValu>
        <labl>$3,000 - 3,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>141</catValu>
        <labl>$3,000 - 3,499</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>142</catValu>
        <labl>$3,500 - 3,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>150</catValu>
        <labl>$4,000 - 4,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>200</catValu>
        <labl>$5,000 - 7,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>210</catValu>
        <labl>$5,000 - 7,499</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>220</catValu>
        <labl>$5,000 - 5,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>230</catValu>
        <labl>$6,000 - 7,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>231</catValu>
        <labl>$6,000 - 7,499</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>232</catValu>
        <labl>$6,000 - 6,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>233</catValu>
        <labl>$7,000 - 7,499</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>234</catValu>
        <labl>$7,000 - 7,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>300</catValu>
        <labl>$7,500 - 9,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>310</catValu>
        <labl>$7,500 - 7,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>320</catValu>
        <labl>$8,000 - 8,499</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>330</catValu>
        <labl>$8,500 - 8,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>340</catValu>
        <labl>$8,000 - 8,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>350</catValu>
        <labl>$9,000 - 9,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>400</catValu>
        <labl>$10,000 - 14,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>410</catValu>
        <labl>$10,000 - 10,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>420</catValu>
        <labl>$11,000 - 11,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>430</catValu>
        <labl>$10,000 - 12,499</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>440</catValu>
        <labl>$10,000 - 11,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>450</catValu>
        <labl>$12,000 - 12,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>460</catValu>
        <labl>$12,000 - 14,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>470</catValu>
        <labl>$12,500 - 14,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>480</catValu>
        <labl>$13,000 - 13,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>490</catValu>
        <labl>$14,000 - 14,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>500</catValu>
        <labl>$15,000 - 19,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>510</catValu>
        <labl>$15,000 - 15,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>520</catValu>
        <labl>$16,000 - 16,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>530</catValu>
        <labl>$17,000 - 17,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>540</catValu>
        <labl>$15,000 - 17,499</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>550</catValu>
        <labl>$17,500 - 19,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>560</catValu>
        <labl>$18,000 - 19,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>600</catValu>
        <labl>$20,000 - 24,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>700</catValu>
        <labl>$25,000 - 49,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>710</catValu>
        <labl>$25,000 - 29,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>720</catValu>
        <labl>$30,000 - 34,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>730</catValu>
        <labl>$35,000 - 39,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>740</catValu>
        <labl>$40,000 - 49,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>800</catValu>
        <labl>$50,000 and over</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>810</catValu>
        <labl>$50,000 - 74,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>820</catValu>
        <labl>$50,000 - 59,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>830</catValu>
        <labl>$60,000 - 74,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>840</catValu>
        <labl>$75,000 and over</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>841</catValu>
        <labl>$75,000 - 99,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>842</catValu>
        <labl>$100,000 - 149,999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>843</catValu>
        <labl>$150,000 and over</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>995</catValu>
        <labl>Missing</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>996</catValu>
        <labl>Refused</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>997</catValu>
        <labl>Don't know</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>999</catValu>
        <labl>Blank</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Economic Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="PERNUM" files="ExtractData" name="PERNUM" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="58" width="2" EndPos="59"/>
      <labl>Person number in sample unit</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[PERNUM numbers all persons within each household consecutively (starting with "1") in the order in which they are listed in the original CPS data.  When combined with YEAR , MONTH, and SERIAL, PERNUM uniquely identifies each person within IPUMS-CPS samples, though not across IPUMS-CPS samples.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
PERNUM is a 2-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="WTFINL" files="ExtractData" name="WTFINL" intrvl="contin" dcml="4">
      <location StartPos="60" width="14" EndPos="73"/>
      <labl>Final Basic Weight</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[WTFINL is the final person-level weight that should be used in analyses of basic monthly data. 

When analyzing ASEC data, researchers should use the person weight WTSUPP. For analyses including the variables EARNWEEK, HOURWAGE, PAIDHOUR, and UNION, researchers should use the EARNWT variable. 

WTFINL is the second stage weight in CPS (see technical documentation [URL omitted from DDI.]). It is based on the inverse probability of selection into the sample and adjustments for the following factors: failure to obtain an interview; sampling within large sample units; adjustments to the known distribution of the entire population according to stage, age, sex, race, and Hispanic ethnicity; and allotting a weight of zero to populations not sampled in other monthly surveys (i.e., persons in the Hispanic oversample and members of the armed forces in ASEC samples).]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
WTFINL is a 14-digit numeric variable with four implied decimals.  That is, 12345678901234 should be interpreted as 1234567890.1234.  The IPUMS command files automatically make the necessary adjustment, so no further adjustment is needed.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="CPSIDP" files="ExtractData" name="CPSIDP" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="74" width="14" EndPos="87"/>
      <labl>CPSID, person record</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[CPSIDP is an IPUMS-CPS defined variable that uniquely identifies individuals across CPS samples. The first six digits of CPSIDP index the four-digit year and two-digit month that the household was first in the CPS. CPSIDP allows users to link a respondent appearing with a designated household roster line number (LINENO) across samples, based on the 4-8-4 rotation pattern, by assigning a unique CPSIDP value to this line number. CPSIDP will only ever appear for a maximum of 8 times, which is the number of times a household may be observed in the CPS survey (as indexed by MISH). In some cases, individuals will appear fewer than 8 times due to migration, mortality, non-response, and recording errors. Extensive documentation about the creation of CPSIDP is available elsewhere [URL omitted from DDI.].

Users should note that it is important to verify CPSIDP linkages with AGE, SEX, and RACE. In some cases CPSIDP will result in erroneous links, which are due to errors in the source data. Cases with the same CPSIDP value may also have inconsistent responses across samples due to errors on the part of the respondent or in recording the response.  Ultimately, it is up to the individual researcher to determine the acceptability of the linkages made using CPSIDP. 

CPSIDP may also be used to link ASEC respondents who are in the March Basic Monthly file to other months of CPS data. This linking is made possible by IPUMS through the creation of MARBASECIDP. 

To get started using CPSIDP, users may want to sort their data file by CPSIDP and MISH to create a person-time file. 

Users should take care when including the March Basic or ASEC as part of their linking. Respondents who are part of the ASEC oversample (as indicated by ASECOVERP) have a CPSIDP value of 0.  For further information about the relationship between the March Basic and the ASEC, please see our additional documentation [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
CPSIDP is a 14-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Linking Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="ASECWT" files="ExtractData" name="ASECWT" intrvl="contin" dcml="4">
      <location StartPos="88" width="10" EndPos="97"/>
      <labl>Annual Social and Economic Supplement Weight</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[ASECWT is a person-level weight that should be used in analyses of individual-level CPS supplement data. Since the CPS relies on a complex stratified sampling scheme, it is essential to use one of the provided weighting variables.

Researchers should use WTFINL rather than ASECWT when they wish to conduct person-level analyses of non-ASEC data. EARNWT should be used for any analysis including a small number of person-level variables (EARNWEEK, HOURWAGE, PAIDHOUR, and UNION). Researchers should use  ASECWTH for household-level analyses.

User Caution: For analyses that include the 2014 ASEC sample, please see the comparability tab.

The ASEC CPS files include two groups of people who are not included in the production of published labor force statistics: (1) members of the armed services, and (2) members of the Hispanic oversample who were interviewed in months other than March. WTFINL and EARNWT assign these groups a value of 0. Both groups are assigned non-zero values in ASECWT.

ASECWT is based on the inverse probability of selection into the sample and adjustments for the following factors: failure to obtain an interview; sampling within large sample units; the known distribution of the entire population according to age, sex, and race; over-sampling Hispanic persons; to give husbands and wives the same weight; and an additional step to provide consistency with labor force estimates from the basic survey. 

Estimates on the entire population are prepared by projecting forward the resident population from the last available census. These projections are derived by updating the demographic census data from a number of other data sources that account for death, births and net migration. About 3 years after every census (i.e. 2003 for the 2000 Census and 2013 for the 2010 Census), the Census Bureau updates its independent population control and provides a new weight for the relevant years.

Two important points should be noted here. First, the lag between when the Census is conducted and when the CPS weights are updated is about 3 years. While the Census data are being processed, the CPS files are made available using the weighting scheme from the US Census prior to the latest Census. Second, once the files are updated, the old weights become obsolete and are replaced in the IPUMS data extract system. Published estimates from the lag years that use the old weights are not always updated. For example, 2010 poverty estimates were released in ASEC using the 2000 population controls. Once the 2010 population controls were made available, IPUMS-CPS replaced the ASEC 2010, 2011, and 2012 weights that are based on the 2000 population control with weights that are based on the 2010 population controls. IPUMS-CPS makes available only the most up-to-date weights.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
ASECWT is a 10-digit numeric variable with four implied decimal places. That is, values of 0012345600 should be interpreted as 1,234.56.  The IPUMS command files automatically divide ASECWT by 10,000, so no further adjustment is needed.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="RELATE" files="ExtractData" name="RELATE" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="98" width="4" EndPos="101"/>
      <labl>Relationship to household head</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[RELATE reports an individual's relationship to the head of household or householder.

CPS interviewers collected detailed information about the precise relationships of all persons in the household in their initial listing of household members.  Unfortunately, they then simplified the detailed data (e.g., daughter-in-law, lodger's brother) by coding it into a few broad categories (e.g., "other relative of head," "nonrelative of head with own relatives in household") specified on the interview form.  Only the broad categories are preserved in the data.  The 4-digit codes for RELATE are consistent with the coding scheme used in IPUMS-USA census data.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>0101</catValu>
        <labl>Head/householder</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>0201</catValu>
        <labl>Spouse</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>0202</catValu>
        <labl>Opposite sex spouse</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>0203</catValu>
        <labl>Same sex spouse</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>0301</catValu>
        <labl>Child</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>0303</catValu>
        <labl>Stepchild</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>0501</catValu>
        <labl>Parent</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>0701</catValu>
        <labl>Sibling</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>0901</catValu>
        <labl>Grandchild</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>1001</catValu>
        <labl>Other relatives, n.s.</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>1113</catValu>
        <labl>Partner/roommate</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>1114</catValu>
        <labl>Unmarried partner</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>1115</catValu>
        <labl>Housemate/roomate</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>1116</catValu>
        <labl>Opposite sex unmarried partner</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>1117</catValu>
        <labl>Same sex unmaried partner</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>1241</catValu>
        <labl>Roomer/boarder/lodger</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>1242</catValu>
        <labl>Foster children</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>1260</catValu>
        <labl>Other nonrelatives</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>9100</catValu>
        <labl>Armed Forces, relationship unknown</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>9200</catValu>
        <labl>Age under 14, relationship unknown</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>9900</catValu>
        <labl>Relationship unknown</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>9999</catValu>
        <labl>NIU</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Demographics Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="AGE" files="ExtractData" name="AGE" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="102" width="2" EndPos="103"/>
      <labl>Age</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[Age gives each person's age at last birthday.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>00</catValu>
        <labl>Under 1 year</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>01</catValu>
        <labl>1</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>02</catValu>
        <labl>2</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>03</catValu>
        <labl>3</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>04</catValu>
        <labl>4</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>05</catValu>
        <labl>5</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>06</catValu>
        <labl>6</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>07</catValu>
        <labl>7</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>08</catValu>
        <labl>8</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>09</catValu>
        <labl>9</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>10</catValu>
        <labl>10</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>11</catValu>
        <labl>11</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>12</catValu>
        <labl>12</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>13</catValu>
        <labl>13</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>14</catValu>
        <labl>14</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>15</catValu>
        <labl>15</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>16</catValu>
        <labl>16</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>17</catValu>
        <labl>17</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>18</catValu>
        <labl>18</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>19</catValu>
        <labl>19</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>20</catValu>
        <labl>20</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>21</catValu>
        <labl>21</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>22</catValu>
        <labl>22</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>23</catValu>
        <labl>23</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>24</catValu>
        <labl>24</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>25</catValu>
        <labl>25</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>26</catValu>
        <labl>26</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>27</catValu>
        <labl>27</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>28</catValu>
        <labl>28</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>29</catValu>
        <labl>29</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>30</catValu>
        <labl>30</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>31</catValu>
        <labl>31</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>32</catValu>
        <labl>32</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>33</catValu>
        <labl>33</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>34</catValu>
        <labl>34</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>35</catValu>
        <labl>35</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>36</catValu>
        <labl>36</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>37</catValu>
        <labl>37</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>38</catValu>
        <labl>38</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>39</catValu>
        <labl>39</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>40</catValu>
        <labl>40</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>41</catValu>
        <labl>41</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>42</catValu>
        <labl>42</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>43</catValu>
        <labl>43</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>44</catValu>
        <labl>44</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>45</catValu>
        <labl>45</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>46</catValu>
        <labl>46</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>47</catValu>
        <labl>47</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>48</catValu>
        <labl>48</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>49</catValu>
        <labl>49</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>50</catValu>
        <labl>50</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>51</catValu>
        <labl>51</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>52</catValu>
        <labl>52</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>53</catValu>
        <labl>53</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>54</catValu>
        <labl>54</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>55</catValu>
        <labl>55</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>56</catValu>
        <labl>56</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>57</catValu>
        <labl>57</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>58</catValu>
        <labl>58</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>59</catValu>
        <labl>59</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60</catValu>
        <labl>60</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>61</catValu>
        <labl>61</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>62</catValu>
        <labl>62</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>63</catValu>
        <labl>63</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>64</catValu>
        <labl>64</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>65</catValu>
        <labl>65</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>66</catValu>
        <labl>66</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>67</catValu>
        <labl>67</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>68</catValu>
        <labl>68</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>69</catValu>
        <labl>69</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>70</catValu>
        <labl>70</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>71</catValu>
        <labl>71</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>72</catValu>
        <labl>72</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>73</catValu>
        <labl>73</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>74</catValu>
        <labl>74</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>75</catValu>
        <labl>75</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>76</catValu>
        <labl>76</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>77</catValu>
        <labl>77</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>78</catValu>
        <labl>78</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>79</catValu>
        <labl>79</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>80</catValu>
        <labl>80</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>81</catValu>
        <labl>81</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>82</catValu>
        <labl>82</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>83</catValu>
        <labl>83</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>84</catValu>
        <labl>84</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>85</catValu>
        <labl>85</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>86</catValu>
        <labl>86</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>87</catValu>
        <labl>87</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>88</catValu>
        <labl>88</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>89</catValu>
        <labl>89</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>90</catValu>
        <labl>90 (90+, 1988-2002)</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>91</catValu>
        <labl>91</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>92</catValu>
        <labl>92</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>93</catValu>
        <labl>93</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>94</catValu>
        <labl>94</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>95</catValu>
        <labl>95</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>96</catValu>
        <labl>96</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>97</catValu>
        <labl>97</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>98</catValu>
        <labl>98</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>99</catValu>
        <labl>99+</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Demographics Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="SEX" files="ExtractData" name="SEX" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="104" width="1" EndPos="104"/>
      <labl>Sex</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[SEX gives each person's sex.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>1</catValu>
        <labl>Male</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>2</catValu>
        <labl>Female</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>9</catValu>
        <labl>NIU</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Demographics Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="RACE" files="ExtractData" name="RACE" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="105" width="3" EndPos="107"/>
      <labl>Race</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[Racial categories in the CPS have been more consistent than racial categories in the census.  Up through 2002, the number of race categories ranged from 3 (white, negro, and other) to 5 (white, black, American Indian/Eskimo/Aleut, Asian or Pacific Islander, and other).   Beginning in 2003, respondents could report more than one race, and the number of codes rose to 21, and then up to 26 codes in 2013.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>999</catValu>
        <labl>Blank</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>820</catValu>
        <labl>Two or three races, unspecified</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>830</catValu>
        <labl>Four or five races, unspecified</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>819</catValu>
        <labl>White-American Indian-Asian-Hawaiian/Pacific Islander</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>804</catValu>
        <labl>White-Hawaiian/Pacific Islander</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>805</catValu>
        <labl>Black-American Indian</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>806</catValu>
        <labl>Black-Asian</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>807</catValu>
        <labl>Black-Hawaiian/Pacific Islander</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>808</catValu>
        <labl>American Indian-Asian</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>809</catValu>
        <labl>Asian-Hawaiian/Pacific Islander</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>810</catValu>
        <labl>White-Black-American Indian</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>811</catValu>
        <labl>White-Black-Asian</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>812</catValu>
        <labl>White-American Indian-Asian</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>813</catValu>
        <labl>White-Asian-Hawaiian/Pacific Islander</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>814</catValu>
        <labl>White-Black-American Indian-Asian</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>815</catValu>
        <labl>American Indian-Hawaiian/Pacific Islander</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>816</catValu>
        <labl>White-Black--Hawaiian/Pacific Islander</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>817</catValu>
        <labl>White-American Indian-Hawaiian/Pacific Islander</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>818</catValu>
        <labl>Black-American Indian-Asian</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>803</catValu>
        <labl>White-Asian</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>801</catValu>
        <labl>White-Black</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>802</catValu>
        <labl>White-American Indian</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>700</catValu>
        <labl>Other (single) race, n.e.c.</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>651</catValu>
        <labl>Asian only</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>652</catValu>
        <labl>Hawaiian/Pacific Islander only</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>650</catValu>
        <labl>Asian or Pacific Islander</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>200</catValu>
        <labl>Black/Negro</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>300</catValu>
        <labl>American Indian/Aleut/Eskimo</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>100</catValu>
        <labl>White</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Demographics Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="MARST" files="ExtractData" name="MARST" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="108" width="1" EndPos="108"/>
      <labl>Marital status</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[MARST gives each person's current marital status, including whether the spouse was currently living in the same household.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>9</catValu>
        <labl>NIU</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>4</catValu>
        <labl>Divorced</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>5</catValu>
        <labl>Widowed</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>6</catValu>
        <labl>Never married/single</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>2</catValu>
        <labl>Married, spouse absent</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>3</catValu>
        <labl>Separated</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>1</catValu>
        <labl>Married, spouse present</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>7</catValu>
        <labl>Widowed or Divorced</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Demographics Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="BPL" files="ExtractData" name="BPL" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="109" width="5" EndPos="113"/>
      <labl>Birthplace</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[BPL indicates whether persons were born in the United States and, if not, the foreign country where they were born.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>96000</catValu>
        <labl>Other, n.e.c. and unknown</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>99999</catValu>
        <labl>NIU</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>72000</catValu>
        <labl>Micronesia</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>71024</catValu>
        <labl>Marshall Islands</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>71021</catValu>
        <labl>Fiji</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>71022</catValu>
        <labl>Tonga</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>71023</catValu>
        <labl>Samoa</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>71000</catValu>
        <labl>Pacific Islands</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>70010</catValu>
        <labl>Australia</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>70020</catValu>
        <labl>New Zealand</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60096</catValu>
        <labl>Congo</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60097</catValu>
        <labl>Zambia</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60099</catValu>
        <labl>Africa, n.s./n.e.c.</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60094</catValu>
        <labl>South Africa (Union of)</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60095</catValu>
        <labl>Zaire</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60065</catValu>
        <labl>Uganda</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60070</catValu>
        <labl>Zimbabwe</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60050</catValu>
        <labl>Somalia</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60060</catValu>
        <labl>Tanzania</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60044</catValu>
        <labl>Ethiopia</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60045</catValu>
        <labl>Kenya</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60039</catValu>
        <labl>Togo</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60040</catValu>
        <labl>Eritrea</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60038</catValu>
        <labl>Ivory Coast</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60036</catValu>
        <labl>Sierra Leone</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60037</catValu>
        <labl>Guinea</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>50000</catValu>
        <labl>China</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>50010</catValu>
        <labl>Hong Kong</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>50040</catValu>
        <labl>Taiwan</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>50100</catValu>
        <labl>Japan</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>50200</catValu>
        <labl>Korea</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>50220</catValu>
        <labl>South Korea</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>50300</catValu>
        <labl>Mongolia</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>51100</catValu>
        <labl>Cambodia</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>51200</catValu>
        <labl>Indonesia</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>51300</catValu>
        <labl>Laos</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>51400</catValu>
        <labl>Malaysia</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>51500</catValu>
        <labl>Philippines</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>51600</catValu>
        <labl>Singapore</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>51700</catValu>
        <labl>Thailand</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>51800</catValu>
        <labl>Vietnam</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>52000</catValu>
        <labl>Afghanistan</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>52100</catValu>
        <labl>India</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>52110</catValu>
        <labl>Bangladesh</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>52120</catValu>
        <labl>Bhutan</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>52130</catValu>
        <labl>Burma</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>52140</catValu>
        <labl>Pakistan</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>52150</catValu>
        <labl>Sri Lanka</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>52200</catValu>
        <labl>Nepal</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>55100</catValu>
        <labl>Armenia</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>55200</catValu>
        <labl>Azerbaijan</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>55300</catValu>
        <labl>Georgia</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>55400</catValu>
        <labl>Uzbekistan</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>55500</catValu>
        <labl>Kazakhstan</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>53000</catValu>
        <labl>Iran</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>53200</catValu>
        <labl>Iraq</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>53400</catValu>
        <labl>Israel</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>53420</catValu>
        <labl>Palestine</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>53500</catValu>
        <labl>Jordan</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>53700</catValu>
        <labl>Lebanon</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>54000</catValu>
        <labl>Saudi Arabia</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>54100</catValu>
        <labl>Syria</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>54200</catValu>
        <labl>Turkey</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>54300</catValu>
        <labl>Cyprus</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>54350</catValu>
        <labl>Kuwait</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>54400</catValu>
        <labl>Yemen</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>54500</catValu>
        <labl>United Arab Emirates</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>54700</catValu>
        <labl>Middle East, n.s.</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>59900</catValu>
        <labl>Asia, n.e.c./n.s.</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60010</catValu>
        <labl>Northern Africa</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60012</catValu>
        <labl>Egypt/United Arab Rep.</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60014</catValu>
        <labl>Morocco</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60016</catValu>
        <labl>Algeria</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60018</catValu>
        <labl>Sudan</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60019</catValu>
        <labl>Libya</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60023</catValu>
        <labl>Ghana</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60031</catValu>
        <labl>Nigeria</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60032</catValu>
        <labl>Cameroon</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60033</catValu>
        <labl>Cape Verde</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60034</catValu>
        <labl>Liberia</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>60035</catValu>
        <labl>Senegal</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>49900</catValu>
        <labl>Europe, n.s.</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>46590</catValu>
        <labl>USSR, n.s.</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>46500</catValu>
        <labl>Other USSR/Russia</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>46530</catValu>
        <labl>Ukraine</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>46535</catValu>
        <labl>Belarus</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>46540</catValu>
        <labl>Moldova</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>46200</catValu>
        <labl>Latvia</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>46300</catValu>
        <labl>Lithuania</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>45760</catValu>
        <labl>Kosovo</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>45770</catValu>
        <labl>Montenego</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>46100</catValu>
        <labl>Estonia</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>45740</catValu>
        <labl>Macedonia</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>45750</catValu>
        <labl>Serbia</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>45730</catValu>
        <labl>Croatia</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>45700</catValu>
        <labl>Yugoslavia</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>45720</catValu>
        <labl>Bosnia and Herzegovina</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>45500</catValu>
        <labl>Poland</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>45600</catValu>
        <labl>Romania</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>45650</catValu>
        <labl>Bulgaria</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>45675</catValu>
        <labl>Albania</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>45400</catValu>
        <labl>Hungary</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>45300</catValu>
        <labl>Germany</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>45212</catValu>
        <labl>Slovakia</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>45213</catValu>
        <labl>Czech Republic</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>43800</catValu>
        <labl>Spain</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>45000</catValu>
        <labl>Austria</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>45200</catValu>
        <labl>Czechoslavakia</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>43400</catValu>
        <labl>Italy</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>43600</catValu>
        <labl>Portugal</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>43610</catValu>
        <labl>Azores</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>42600</catValu>
        <labl>Switzerland</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>43300</catValu>
        <labl>Greece</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>42500</catValu>
        <labl>Netherlands</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>42100</catValu>
        <labl>France</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>42000</catValu>
        <labl>Belgium</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>41410</catValu>
        <labl>Northern Ireland</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>41300</catValu>
        <labl>United Kingdom, n.s.</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>41400</catValu>
        <labl>Ireland</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>41200</catValu>
        <labl>Wales</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>41100</catValu>
        <labl>Scotland</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>41000</catValu>
        <labl>England</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>40500</catValu>
        <labl>Sweden</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>40400</catValu>
        <labl>Norway</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>40200</catValu>
        <labl>Iceland</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>40100</catValu>
        <labl>Finland</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>40000</catValu>
        <labl>Denmark</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>31000</catValu>
        <labl>Americas, n.s.</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>30090</catValu>
        <labl>South America, n.s.</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>30070</catValu>
        <labl>Paraguay</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>30065</catValu>
        <labl>Venezuela</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>30050</catValu>
        <labl>Peru</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>30060</catValu>
        <labl>Uruguay</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>30040</catValu>
        <labl>Guyana/British Guiana</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>30030</catValu>
        <labl>Ecuador</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>30025</catValu>
        <labl>Colombia</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>30020</catValu>
        <labl>Chile</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>30015</catValu>
        <labl>Brazil</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>30005</catValu>
        <labl>Argentina</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>30010</catValu>
        <labl>Bolivia</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>26091</catValu>
        <labl>Caribbean, n.s.</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>26075</catValu>
        <labl>St. Lucia</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>26080</catValu>
        <labl>St. Vincent and the Grenadi</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>26070</catValu>
        <labl>St. Kitts--Nevis</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>10000</catValu>
        <labl>American Samoa</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>10500</catValu>
        <labl>Guam</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>10750</catValu>
        <labl>Northern Mariana Islands</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>11000</catValu>
        <labl>Puerto Rico</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>26060</catValu>
        <labl>Trinidad and Tobago</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>26055</catValu>
        <labl>Grenada</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>26044</catValu>
        <labl>Barbados</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>26054</catValu>
        <labl>Dominica</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>26043</catValu>
        <labl>Bahamas</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>26020</catValu>
        <labl>Haiti</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>26030</catValu>
        <labl>Jamaica</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>26010</catValu>
        <labl>Dominican Republic</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>25000</catValu>
        <labl>Cuba</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>21070</catValu>
        <labl>Panama</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>21090</catValu>
        <labl>Central America, n.s.</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>21060</catValu>
        <labl>Nicaragua</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>21050</catValu>
        <labl>Honduras</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>21040</catValu>
        <labl>Guatemala</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>21020</catValu>
        <labl>Costa Rica</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>21030</catValu>
        <labl>El Salvador</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>21010</catValu>
        <labl>Belize/British Honduras</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>20000</catValu>
        <labl>Mexico</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>19900</catValu>
        <labl>North America, n.s.</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>15000</catValu>
        <labl>Canada</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>16010</catValu>
        <labl>Bermuda</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>11500</catValu>
        <labl>U.S. Virgin Islands</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>12090</catValu>
        <labl>U.S. outlying areas, n.s.</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>09900</catValu>
        <labl>United States, n.s.</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>26065</catValu>
        <labl>Antigua and Barbuda</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Ethnicity/Nativity Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="CITIZEN" files="ExtractData" name="CITIZEN" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="114" width="1" EndPos="114"/>
      <labl>Citizenship status</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[CITIZEN reports the citizenship status of foreign-born persons.  In IPUMS-CPS, people born in the U.S., Puerto Rico, or U.S. outlying areas were excluded from the question universe.  Respondents were identified as belonging to one of three groups: citizens by virtue of being born abroad to American parents; naturalized citizens; and non-citizens.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>1</catValu>
        <labl>Born in U.S</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>2</catValu>
        <labl>Born in U.S. outlying</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>3</catValu>
        <labl>Born abroad of American parents</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>4</catValu>
        <labl>Naturalized citizen</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>5</catValu>
        <labl>Not a citizen</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>9</catValu>
        <labl>NIU</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Ethnicity/Nativity Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="EMPSTAT" files="ExtractData" name="EMPSTAT" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="115" width="2" EndPos="116"/>
      <labl>Employment status</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[EMPSTAT indicates whether persons were part of the labor force--working or seeking work--and, if so, whether they were currently unemployed.  The variable also provides information on the activity (e.g., doing housework, attending school,) or status (e.g., retired, unable to work) of persons not in the labor force, as well as limited additional information on those who are in the labor force (e.g. members of the Armed Forces, those with a job, but not at work last week).  See LABFORCE for a dichotomous variable identifying whether a person participated in the labor force.

In the CPS, individuals' employment status was determined on the basis of answers to a series of questions relating to their activities during the preceding week.  Those who reported doing any work at all for pay or profit, or working at least fifteen hours without pay in a family business or farm, were classified as "at work."  Those who did not work during the previous week but who acknowledged having a job or business from which they were temporarily absent (e.g., due to illness, vacation, bad weather, or labor dispute) were also classified as employed, under the heading "has job, not at work last week."  

Because the CPS is designed to measure unemployment in the civilian population, the original employment status variable in the survey classifies members of the armed forces as NIU (Not in universe).

Unemployed persons make up the third element of the labor force.  Individuals were coded as unemployed if they did no work for pay or profit, did not have a job from which they were briefly absent, and either reported looking for work as their major activity during the previous week (for 1962 through 1993) or answered yes to a question about whether they had been looking for work in the past four weeks.  People who were temporarily laid off from a job were also classified as unemployed.   A separate CPS variable specifying whether an unemployed person had worked before or was looking for a first job was used to distinguish between "experienced" and "inexperienced" unemployed persons in IPUMS-CPS.

Persons who were neither employed nor unemployed fall into the residual category, "not in labor force."  Such individuals might be retired, disabled due to an illness lasting at least 6 months, occupied with other activities such as attending school or keeping house, or convinced that they are unlikely to find employment (discouraged workers).]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>00</catValu>
        <labl>NIU</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>01</catValu>
        <labl>Armed Forces</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>10</catValu>
        <labl>At work</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>12</catValu>
        <labl>Has job, not at work last week</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>20</catValu>
        <labl>Unemployed</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>21</catValu>
        <labl>Unemployed, experienced worker</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>22</catValu>
        <labl>Unemployed, new worker</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>30</catValu>
        <labl>Not in labor force</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>31</catValu>
        <labl>NILF, housework</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>32</catValu>
        <labl>NILF, unable to work</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>33</catValu>
        <labl>NILF, school</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>34</catValu>
        <labl>NILF, other</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>35</catValu>
        <labl>NILF, unpaid, lt 15 hours</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>36</catValu>
        <labl>NILF, retired</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="LABFORCE" files="ExtractData" name="LABFORCE" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="117" width="1" EndPos="117"/>
      <labl>Labor force status</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[LABFORCE is a dichotomous variable indicating whether the respondent participated in the labor force during the preceding week.  See EMPSTAT for a more detailed employment status variable.   Those coded as "yes" in LABFORCE were either: were at work; held a job but were temporarily absent from work due to factors like vacation or illness; were seeking work; or were temporarily laid off from a job during the reference period.  

Because the CPS is designed to measure unemployment in the civilian population, the original dichotomous employment status variable in the survey classifies members of the armed forces as NIU (Not in universe).]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>0</catValu>
        <labl>NIU</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>1</catValu>
        <labl>No, not in the labor force</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>2</catValu>
        <labl>Yes, in the labor force</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="OCC" files="ExtractData" name="OCC" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="118" width="4" EndPos="121"/>
      <labl>Occupation</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[OCC reports the person's primary occupation.  Respondents who held more than one job were to report the job at which they worked the largest number of hours.  For persons who were employed at the time of the survey, OCC relates to the job worked during the preceding week; unemployed persons and those not currently in the labor force were to give their most recent occupation.   The CPS interviewer collected information by asking what kind of work the person was doing, and Census Bureau staff coded the information into the contemporary CPS or census occupational classification.  Researchers who wish to work with a consistent occupational coding scheme for 1968 forward should use the OCC1950 variable.  For general discussion of employment concepts, including the definition of those not in the labor force, see the documentation on EMPSTAT.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
OCC is a 4-digit numeric variable.
(Codes for 1962-1967 are 2 digits; each is preceded by two zeros).
(Codes for 1968-2002 are 3 digits; each is preceded by a zero in the first position.)

1962-1967 [URL omitted from DDI.]  
1968-1970 [URL omitted from DDI.]
1971-1982 [URL omitted from DDI.]
1983-1991 [URL omitted from DDI.]
1992-2002 [URL omitted from DDI.]
2003-2010 [URL omitted from DDI.]
2011+ [URL omitted from DDI.]]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="IND" files="ExtractData" name="IND" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="122" width="4" EndPos="125"/>
      <labl>Industry</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[IND reports the type of industry in which the person performed his or her primary occupation, which is recorded in the variables OCC (Occupation) and, after 1968, OCC1950 (Occupation, 1950 basis).  "Industry" refers to the work setting and economic sector, while "occupation" relates to the worker's specific technical function.
  
For persons who were employed at the time of the survey, IND relates to the industrial sector in which the respondent worked during the preceding week.  For unemployed persons and those not currently in the labor force, IND characterizes the industrial sector of the respondent's most recent job.   The CPS interviewer collected information by asking what kind of work the person was doing, and Census Bureau staff coded the information into the CPS or census industrial classification.  Researchers who wish to work with a consistent industrial coding scheme for 1968 forward should use the IND1950 variable.  For general discussion of employment concepts, including the definition of those not in the labor force, see the documentation on EMPSTAT.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
IND is a 4-digit numeric variable.
(Codes for 1962-1967 are 2 digits; each is preceded by two zeroes in the first positions.)
(Codes for 1968-2002 are 3 digits; each is preceded by a zero in the first position.)

1962 [URL omitted from DDI.]
1963-1967 [URL omitted from DDI.]
1968-1970 [URL omitted from DDI.]
1971-1982 [URL omitted from DDI.]
1983-1991 [URL omitted from DDI.]
1992-2002 [URL omitted from DDI.]
2003-2008 [URL omitted from DDI.]
2009-2013 [URL omitted from DDI.]
2014-onward [URL omitted from DDI.]]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="EDUC" files="ExtractData" name="EDUC" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="126" width="3" EndPos="128"/>
      <labl>Educational attainment recode</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[EDUC indicates respondents' educational attainment, as measured by the highest year of school or degree completed. Note that completion differs from the highest year of school attendance; for example, respondents who attended 10th grade but did not finish were classified in EDUC as having completed 9th grade. 

EDUC is a combination of two other variables, HIGRADE and EDUC99, which measure educational attainment in different ways.  HIGRADE is available for years prior to 1992 and gives the respondent's highest grade of school or year of college completed.  EDUC99 is available beginning in 1992 and classifies high school graduates according to their highest degree or diploma attained.  

General and detailed codes are not yet available for IPUMS-CPS, but one can construct the general version of EDUC by reading only the first two columns of EDUC.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>021</catValu>
        <labl>Grade 5</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>022</catValu>
        <labl>Grade 6</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>999</catValu>
        <labl>Missing/Unknown</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>125</catValu>
        <labl>Doctorate degree</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>124</catValu>
        <labl>Professional school degree</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>122</catValu>
        <labl>6+ years of college</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>123</catValu>
        <labl>Master's degree</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>121</catValu>
        <labl>5 years of college</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>111</catValu>
        <labl>Bachelor's degree</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>120</catValu>
        <labl>5+ years of college</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>110</catValu>
        <labl>4 years of college</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>092</catValu>
        <labl>Associate's degree, academic program</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>100</catValu>
        <labl>3 years of college</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>091</catValu>
        <labl>Associate's degree, occupational/vocational program</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>090</catValu>
        <labl>2 years of college</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>081</catValu>
        <labl>Some college but no degree</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>073</catValu>
        <labl>High school diploma or equivalent</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>080</catValu>
        <labl>1 year of college</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>072</catValu>
        <labl>12th grade, diploma unclear</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>071</catValu>
        <labl>12th grade, no diploma</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>070</catValu>
        <labl>Grade 12</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>060</catValu>
        <labl>Grade 11</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>050</catValu>
        <labl>Grade 10</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>032</catValu>
        <labl>Grade 8</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>040</catValu>
        <labl>Grade 9</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>030</catValu>
        <labl>Grades 7 or 8</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>031</catValu>
        <labl>Grade 7</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>014</catValu>
        <labl>Grade 4</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>020</catValu>
        <labl>Grades 5 or 6</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>013</catValu>
        <labl>Grade 3</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>011</catValu>
        <labl>Grade 1</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>012</catValu>
        <labl>Grade 2</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>010</catValu>
        <labl>Grades 1, 2, 3, or 4</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>001</catValu>
        <labl>NIU or blank</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>002</catValu>
        <labl>None or preschool</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>000</catValu>
        <labl>NIU or no schooling</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Education Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="OCCLY" files="ExtractData" name="OCCLY" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="129" width="4" EndPos="132"/>
      <labl>Occupation last year</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[OCCLY reports the person's primary occupation during the previous calendar year.  A respondent who held more than one job during the preceding year was to report the job that lasted longest. The reference period for OCCLY, the preceding calendar year, is the same as the reference period for income variables in IPUMS-CPS.

The CPS interviewer collected information by asking what kind of work the person was doing during the preceding calendar year, and Census Bureau staff coded the information into the CPS or census occupational classification. Researchers who wish to work with a consistent occupational coding scheme for 1968 forward should use the OCC50LY variable.  

The occupation of persons employed at the time of the survey is reported in OCC.  OCC also provides information about the most recent job for persons not in the labor force at the time of the survey.  For general discussion of employment concepts, including the definition of those not in the labor force, see the documentation on EMPSTAT.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
OCCLY is a 3-digit numeric variable for 1962-2002 and a 4-digit numeric variable for 2003 and on. Codes are the same as those for OCC, except in 1962-1967. 

1962-1967 OCCLY codes [URL omitted from DDI.]  
1968-1970 OCC and OCCLY codes [URL omitted from DDI.]  
1971-1982 OCC and OCCLY codes [URL omitted from DDI.]  
1983-1991 OCC and OCCLY codes [URL omitted from DDI.]  
1992-2002 OCC and OCCLY codes [URL omitted from DDI.]  
2003-2010 OCC and OCCLY codes  [URL omitted from DDI.]]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INDLY" files="ExtractData" name="INDLY" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="133" width="4" EndPos="136"/>
      <labl>Industry last year</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INDLY reports the industry in which the respondent worked during the previous calendar year.  A respondent who held more than one job during the preceding year was to report the job that lasted longest.   The reference period for INDLY, the preceding calendar year, is the same as the reference period for income variables in IPUMS-CPS.

The CPS interviewer collected information by asking what kind of work the person was doing last year, and Census Bureau staff coded the information into the CPS or census industrial classification.  Researchers who wish to work with a consistent occupational coding scheme for 1968-2002 should use the IND50LY variable.  

The industry of persons employed at the time of the survey is reported in IND.  IND also provides information about the most recent job for persons not in the labor force at the time of the survey.  For general discussion of employment concepts, including the definition of those not in the labor force, see the documentation on EMPSTAT.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
INDLY is a 3-digit numeric variable. Codes are the same as those for IND.
(Codes for 1962-1967 are 2 digits; each is preceded by a zero in the first position).

1962-1967 [URL omitted from DDI.]  
1968-1970 [URL omitted from DDI.]  
1971-1982 [URL omitted from DDI.]  
1983-1991 [URL omitted from DDI.]  
1992-2002 [URL omitted from DDI.]  
2003-2008 [URL omitted from DDI.]
2009-2013 [URL omitted from DDI.]
2014-onward [URL omitted from DDI.]]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="CLASSWLY" files="ExtractData" name="CLASSWLY" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="137" width="2" EndPos="138"/>
      <labl>Class of worker last year</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[CLASSWLY specifies whether a person who worked during the previous calendar year was self-employed, an employee in private industry or the public sector, in the armed forces, or worked without pay in a family business or farm.  Respondents were classified by the job that they held for the longest time during the previous year.  More specific information about an individual's job during this period is given in OCCLY, OCC50LY, INDLY, and IND50LY.  

CLASSWKR relates to the respondent's job during the previous week, rather than the previous year.  CLASSWKR also reports the most recent job for respondents who were not employed in the week prior to the survey.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>29</catValu>
        <labl>Unpaid family worker</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>99</catValu>
        <labl>Missing/Unknown</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>28</catValu>
        <labl>Local government employee</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>27</catValu>
        <labl>State government employee</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>25</catValu>
        <labl>Federal government employee</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>24</catValu>
        <labl>Wage/salary, government</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>00</catValu>
        <labl>NIU</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>10</catValu>
        <labl>Self-employed</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>13</catValu>
        <labl>Self-employed, not incorporated</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>14</catValu>
        <labl>Self-employed, incorporated</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>22</catValu>
        <labl>Wage/salary, private</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>20</catValu>
        <labl>Works for wages or salary</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="WORKLY" files="ExtractData" name="WORKLY" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="139" width="2" EndPos="140"/>
      <labl>Worked last year</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[WORKLY indicates whether or not the respondent worked any time in the calendar year previous to the survey year.  For example, if the respondent is interviewed in March of 2015, they are reporting whether they had worked any time in 2014.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>00</catValu>
        <labl>NIU</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>01</catValu>
        <labl>No</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>02</catValu>
        <labl>Yes</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="UHRSWORKLY" files="ExtractData" name="UHRSWORKLY" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="141" width="3" EndPos="143"/>
      <labl>Usual hours worked per week (last yr)</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[UHRSWORKLY reports the number of hours per week that respondents usually worked if they worked during the previous calendar year.  Individuals were asked this question if: 1) they reported working at a job or business at any time during the previous year or 2) they acknowledged doing "any temporary, part-time, or seasonal work even for a few days" during the previous year.  

See the Hours Worked Variables Notes [URL omitted from DDI.] for an overview of the different actual and usual hours worked variables available.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
UHRSWORKLY is a 2-digit numeric value.

99 = 99 hours or more
999 = NIU (Not in universe)]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="WKSUNEM1" files="ExtractData" name="WKSUNEM1" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="144" width="2" EndPos="145"/>
      <labl>Weeks unemployed last year</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[WKSUNEM1 gives the number of weeks, in single weeks, that the respondent looked for work or was on layoff during the preceding calendar year.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
WKSUNEM1 is a 2-digit numeric value.

99 = N.I.U.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="FULLPART" files="ExtractData" name="FULLPART" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="146" width="1" EndPos="146"/>
      <labl>Worked full or part time last year</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[FULLPART indicates whether respondents who were employed during the previous calendar year worked full-time or part-time.  Full-time work is defined as thirty-five hours a week or more.   Beginning in 1976, more detailed information on hours worked during the previous year is available in UHRSWORKLY.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>0</catValu>
        <labl>NIU</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>1</catValu>
        <labl>Full-time</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>2</catValu>
        <labl>Part-time</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>9</catValu>
        <labl>Unknown</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="NWLOOKWK" files="ExtractData" name="NWLOOKWK" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="147" width="2" EndPos="148"/>
      <labl>Weeks looked for work last year (didn't work)</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[For civilian adults who did not work during the preceding calendar year, NWLOOK reports the number of weeks such persons spent looking for work or on layoff. 

After ascertaining that the individual did not work, even for a few days, during the previous calendar year, the interviewer asked, "Even though you did not work in [year], did you spend any time trying to find a job or on layoff?"  If the answer was yes, the interviewer asked, "How many different weeks were you looking for work or on layoff?"   Responses to this second question are recorded in NWLOOKWK.  A code of "00" indicates that the individual did not work during the preceding calendar year and spent no weeks looking for work or on layoff during this period.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>00</catValu>
        <labl>Did not look for work/wasn't on layoff</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>01</catValu>
        <labl>1 week</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>02</catValu>
        <labl>2 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>03</catValu>
        <labl>3 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>04</catValu>
        <labl>4 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>05</catValu>
        <labl>5 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>06</catValu>
        <labl>6 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>07</catValu>
        <labl>7 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>08</catValu>
        <labl>8 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>09</catValu>
        <labl>9 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>10</catValu>
        <labl>10 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>11</catValu>
        <labl>11 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>12</catValu>
        <labl>12 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>13</catValu>
        <labl>13 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>14</catValu>
        <labl>14 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>15</catValu>
        <labl>15 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>16</catValu>
        <labl>16 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>17</catValu>
        <labl>17 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>18</catValu>
        <labl>18 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>19</catValu>
        <labl>19 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>20</catValu>
        <labl>20 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>21</catValu>
        <labl>21 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>22</catValu>
        <labl>22 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>23</catValu>
        <labl>23 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>24</catValu>
        <labl>24 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>25</catValu>
        <labl>25 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>26</catValu>
        <labl>26 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>27</catValu>
        <labl>27 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>28</catValu>
        <labl>28 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>29</catValu>
        <labl>29 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>30</catValu>
        <labl>30 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>31</catValu>
        <labl>31 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>32</catValu>
        <labl>32 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>33</catValu>
        <labl>33 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>34</catValu>
        <labl>34 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>35</catValu>
        <labl>35 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>36</catValu>
        <labl>36 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>37</catValu>
        <labl>37 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>38</catValu>
        <labl>38 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>39</catValu>
        <labl>39 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>40</catValu>
        <labl>40 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>41</catValu>
        <labl>41 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>42</catValu>
        <labl>42 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>43</catValu>
        <labl>43 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>44</catValu>
        <labl>44 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>45</catValu>
        <labl>45 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>46</catValu>
        <labl>46 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>47</catValu>
        <labl>47 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>48</catValu>
        <labl>48 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>49</catValu>
        <labl>49 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>50</catValu>
        <labl>50 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>51</catValu>
        <labl>51 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>52</catValu>
        <labl>52 weeks</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>99</catValu>
        <labl>NIU</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="FIRMSIZE" files="ExtractData" name="FIRMSIZE" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="149" width="1" EndPos="149"/>
      <labl>Number of employees</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[FIRMSIZE indicates the total number of persons who worked for the respondent's employer during the preceding calendar year, counting all locations where the employer operated.  If the individual was self-employed in a business or farm, the response to FIRMSIZE indicates how many employees worked for the respondent.   Responses were grouped into broad categories, such as "under 25 employees," "25 to 99 employees," "100 to 499 employees," "500 to 999 employees," and "1000+ employees."]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>0</catValu>
        <labl>NIU</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>1</catValu>
        <labl>Under 10</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>2</catValu>
        <labl>10 to 24</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>3</catValu>
        <labl>Under 25</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>4</catValu>
        <labl>10 to 49</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>5</catValu>
        <labl>25 to 99</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>6</catValu>
        <labl>50 to 99</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>7</catValu>
        <labl>100 to 499</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>8</catValu>
        <labl>500 to 999</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>9</catValu>
        <labl>1000+</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="WANTJOB" files="ExtractData" name="WANTJOB" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="150" width="1" EndPos="150"/>
      <labl>Want regular job now</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[WANTJOB reports whether respondents not in the labor force (neither working, nor temporarily absent from a job, nor actively looking for work) wanted a job, either full- or part-time.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>0</catValu>
        <labl>NIU</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>1</catValu>
        <labl>No</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>2</catValu>
        <labl>Yes</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>3</catValu>
        <labl>Maybe, it depends</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>4</catValu>
        <labl>Do not know</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>9</catValu>
        <labl>Unknown</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="FTOTVAL" files="ExtractData" name="FTOTVAL" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="151" width="10" EndPos="160"/>
      <labl>Total family income</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[FTOTVAL reports the total income for the respondent's family. Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer (i.e., in the survey year's dollar amounts). Users may want to adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
Note: Values are as they appear in the original CPS data. Top-codes, bottom-codes, and NIU codes have not been harmonized by the IPUMS.

1968-1975
50000 = Top Code (50,000 and greater)
999999 = NIU 

Values in all years can be negative.


See User Note [URL omitted from DDI.] for an explanation of these codes.]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INCTOT" files="ExtractData" name="INCTOT" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="161" width="9" EndPos="169"/>
      <labl>Total personal income</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INCTOT indicates each respondent's total pre-tax personal income or losses from all sources for the previous calendar year.  Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
999999999 = N.I.U.
999999998 = Missing. (1962-1964 only)
Values can be negative.

The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INCWAGE" files="ExtractData" name="INCWAGE" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="170" width="8" EndPos="177"/>
      <labl>Wage and salary income</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INCWAGE indicates each respondent's total pre-tax wage and salary income--that is, money received as an employee--for the previous calendar year.  Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors. 

For ASEC samples 1988-onward, INCWAGE is derived from a Census recode variable.  The topcoded components of INCWAGE are OINCWAGE and INCLONGJ.  OINCWAGE  is always a component of INCWAGE.  When SRCEARN indicates that INCLONGJ is earned from wage and salary, INCLONGJ is an additional component of INCWAGE.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
99999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe)
99999998 = Missing (1962-1964 only)

The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INCBUS" files="ExtractData" name="INCBUS" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="178" width="8" EndPos="185"/>
      <labl>Non-farm business income</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INCBUS indicates each respondent's net pre-income-tax non-farm business and/or professional practice income for the previous calendar year.  INCBUS is reported for self-employed persons; employees' earnings are given in INCWAGE.   

Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors. 

For ASEC samples 1988-onward, INCBUS is derived from a Census recode variable.  The topcoded components of INCBUS are OINCBUS and INCLONGJ.  OINCBUS  is always a component of INCBUS.  When SRCEARN indicates that INCLONGJ is earned from self-employment, INCLONGJ is an additional component of INCBUS.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
99999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).
99999998 = Missing. (1962-1964 only)
Values can be negative.

The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INCFARM" files="ExtractData" name="INCFARM" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="186" width="8" EndPos="193"/>
      <labl>Farm income</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INCFARM indicates each respondent's net pre-income-tax earnings as a tenant farmer, sharecropper, or operator of his or her own farm during the previous calendar year.  INCFARM collects income information for self-employed persons who had their own farms.  Income earned as an employee on a farm is contained in the variable INCWAGE.  

Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors. 

For ASEC samples 1988-onward, INCFARM is derived from a Census recode variable.  The topcoded components of INCFARM are OINCFARM and INCLONGJ.  OINCFARM  is always a component of INCFARM.  When SRCEARN indicates that INCLONGJ is earned from farm self-employment, INCLONGJ is an additional component of INCFARM.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
99999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe)
99999998 = Missing (1962-1964 only)
Values can be negative.

The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INCSS" files="ExtractData" name="INCSS" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="194" width="6" EndPos="199"/>
      <labl>Social Security income</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INCSS indicates how much pre-tax income (if any) the respondent received from Social Security or U.S. government Railroad Retirement insurance payments (for 1968-1979) or from Social Security payments exclusively (1980 forward).  

Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).


The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INCWELFR" files="ExtractData" name="INCWELFR" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="200" width="6" EndPos="205"/>
      <labl>Welfare (public assistance) income</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INCWELFR indicates how much pre-tax income (if any) the respondent received during the previous calendar year from various public assistance programs commonly referred to as "welfare."

Totals are given as they were reported to CPS interviewers; users must adjust for the effects of inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).


The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INCRETIR" files="ExtractData" name="INCRETIR" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="206" width="8" EndPos="213"/>
      <labl>Retirement income</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INCRETIR indicates how much pre-tax income (if any) the respondent received from all retirement income sources during the past year. Pension or retirement income from a previous employer or union, or from other retirement income (excluding Social Security and Veterans' Administration payments) are included as sources prior to 2019. During this period, the survey questionnaire listed the following types of retirement income: company or union pension, including profit sharing; annuities; U.S. military retirement; federal government employee pensions; state or local government employee pensions; U.S. Railroad Retirement; regular payments from annuities or paid-up insurance policies; and other sources such as IRA or KEOUGH accounts. 

Beginning in 2019, income from retirement accounts, pension plans, and annuities are split into separate variables. INCRETIR includes only income from retirement accounts, and not pension plans or annuities. Retirement account income from 401k, 403b, Roth IRA, regular IRA, KEOGH, and Simplified Employee Pension (SEP) plans are included.

Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
99999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).


The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INCSSI" files="ExtractData" name="INCSSI" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="214" width="6" EndPos="219"/>
      <labl>Income from SSI</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INCSSI indicates how much pre-tax income (if any) the respondent received from Supplemental Security Income (SSI) during the previous calendar year.

Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).


The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INCINT" files="ExtractData" name="INCINT" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="220" width="7" EndPos="226"/>
      <labl>Income from interest</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INCINT indicates how much pre-tax income (if any) the respondent received from  interest on saving accounts, certificates of deposit, money market funds, bonds, treasury notes, IRAs, and/or other investments which paid interest.

Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
9999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).


The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INCUNEMP" files="ExtractData" name="INCUNEMP" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="227" width="6" EndPos="232"/>
      <labl>Income from unemployment benefits</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INCUNEMP indicates how much pre-tax income (if any) the respondent received from state or federal unemployment compensation, Supplemental Unemployment Benefits (SUB), or union unemployment or strike benefits during the previous calendar year.  

Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe)


The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INCWKCOM" files="ExtractData" name="INCWKCOM" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="233" width="6" EndPos="238"/>
      <labl>Income from worker's compensation</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INCWKCOM indicates how much pre-tax income (if any) the respondent received from worker's compensation payments or other payments as a result as a job-related injury or illness.  Income from sick pay and disability retirement were not counted as income under INCWKCOM.

Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).


The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INCVET" files="ExtractData" name="INCVET" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="239" width="7" EndPos="245"/>
      <labl>Income from veteran's benefits</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INCVET indicates how much pre-tax income (if any) the respondent received from payments from the Veterans' Administration (VA) during the previous calendar year.  Such payments could include service-related disability compensation, survivor benefits, pension, educational allowance, or other veteran payments.

Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
9999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).


The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INCSURV" files="ExtractData" name="INCSURV" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="246" width="7" EndPos="252"/>
      <labl>Income from survivor's benefits</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INCSURV indicates how much pre-tax income (if any) the respondent received from survivors' benefits during the previous calendar year.  Such payments could include the following: company or union survivor pension; federal government civil service pension; U.S. military retirement survivor pension; state or local government survivor pension; worker's compensation survivor pension; black lung survivor pension; regular payments from an estate or trust; and regular payments from annuities or paid-up insurance policies.  Social Security and Veterans' Administration payments were specifically excluded from this category; payments from these sources are given in INCSS and INCVET, respectively.

Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
9999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).


The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INCDISAB" files="ExtractData" name="INCDISAB" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="253" width="7" EndPos="259"/>
      <labl>Income from disability benefits</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INCDISAB indicates how much pre-tax income (if any) the respondent received from disability income during the previous calendar year.   

CPS interviewers asked about income as a result of disability only if at least one member of the household had "a health condition or disability which prevents them from working or which limits the kind or amount of work they can do" or had "ever retired or left a job for health reasons."  If the answer was affirmative, the interviewer asked which household member (or members) had such a health condition and whether this person received income as a result of this health condition, disability, or handicap.

Income due to disability could come from the following sources: worker's compensation; company or union disability; federal government civil service disability; U.S. military retirement disability; state or local government employee disability; U.S. Railroad Retirement disability; accident or disability insurance; black lung miner's disability; or state temporary sickness payments. Income from Social Security and payments from the Veterans' Administration were not included in INCDISAB; such payments were included in INCSS and INCVET, respectively.  

Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
9999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).


The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INCDIVID" files="ExtractData" name="INCDIVID" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="260" width="7" EndPos="266"/>
      <labl>Income from dividends</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INCDIVID indicates how much pre-tax income (if any) the respondent received from stocks and mutual funds during the previous calendar year.

Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
9999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).

The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INCRENT" files="ExtractData" name="INCRENT" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="267" width="7" EndPos="273"/>
      <labl>Income from rent</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INCRENT indicates how much pre-tax income (if any) the respondent received from rent (after expenses), from charges to roomers or boarders, and from money paid by estates, trusts, and royalties, during the previous calendar year.

Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
9999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).


The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INCEDUC" files="ExtractData" name="INCEDUC" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="274" width="6" EndPos="279"/>
      <labl>Income from educational assistance</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INCEDUC indicates how much pre-tax income (if any) the respondent received from educational assistance during the previous calendar year.  This variable relates to education beyond the high school level, including college, university, or vocational, business, or trade school.  The financial aid could cover tuition, fees, books, or living expenses while attending school.  

Educational assistance includes Pell Grants or other aid from government sources, non-governmental scholarships and grants, and financial assistance from employers or friends (excluding household members).  Educational benefits from the Veteran's Administration are included in INCVET rather than INCEDUC.

Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).


The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INCCHILD" files="ExtractData" name="INCCHILD" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="280" width="6" EndPos="285"/>
      <labl>Income from child support</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INCCHILD indicates how much pre-tax income (if any) the respondent received from child support payments during the previous calendar year. 

Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).


The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INCASIST" files="ExtractData" name="INCASIST" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="286" width="7" EndPos="292"/>
      <labl>Income from assistance</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INCASIST indicates how much pre-tax income (if any) the respondent received during the previous calendar year from regular financial assistance from friends or relatives not living in the same household. 

Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
9999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).


The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INCOTHER" files="ExtractData" name="INCOTHER" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="293" width="7" EndPos="299"/>
      <labl>Income from other Source not specified</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INCOTHER is a residual category for pre-tax income for the previous calendar year that was not reported in other, more specific, income variables.  Small amounts of income from hobbies, severance pay, and foster child care payments are included in INCOTHER, as is any income that respondents failed to report earlier in the interview.  

INCOTHER covers income not captured in the variables INCWAGE, INCBUS, INCFARM, INCSS, INCWELFR, INCRETIR, INCSSI, INCINT, INCUNEMP, INCWKCOM, INCVET, INCSURV, INCDISAB, INCRENT, INCDIVID, INCEDUC, INCCHILD, INCALIM, and INCASIST.

Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
9999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).


The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INCRANN" files="ExtractData" name="INCRANN" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="300" width="6" EndPos="305"/>
      <labl>Retirement income from annuities</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INCRANN reports the amount of retirement income from annuities respondents received during the previous calendar year. 

Prior to 2019, retirement income from annuities was reported in INCRETI1 or INCRETI2 for those who reported annuities as a source of retirement income in SRCRETI1 and SRCRETI2, respectively.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[INCRANN is a 6-digit numeric variable.

		
0 = NIU]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INCPENS" files="ExtractData" name="INCPENS" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="306" width="7" EndPos="312"/>
      <labl>Pension income</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INCPENS reports the total amount of pension income the respondent received during the previous calendar year from all sources. These source are identified in SRCPEN1 and SRCPEN2.  Amounts received from these individual sources are found in INCPEN1 and INCPEN2.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[INCPENS is a 7-digit numeric variable.

		
0 = NIU]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INCLONGJ" files="ExtractData" name="INCLONGJ" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="313" width="8" EndPos="320"/>
      <labl>Earnings from longest job</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INCLONGJ reports the net amount (prior to deductions) that the respondent earned from the job held for the longest time during the preceding calendar year.  Whether such income derived from wages or salary or from self-employment in a business or farm is specified in SRCEARN.

Most income variables included in IPUMS-CPS report the total amount earned from a specific source (e.g., wages and salary) during the preceding calendar year.  INCLONGJ, by contrast, does not necessarily include income earned during the entire calendar year.  Imagine that an individual worked at one job for eight months, earning $10,000 in wages, and then worked for four months at two different jobs, earning an additional $5000 in wages.  Wages from the longest-held job (in this case, $10,000) would be reported in INCLONGJ.  Wage and salary income from the two jobs other than the longest-held job (in this case, $5,000) would be reported in OINCWAGE. Total earnings from wages for this person (in this case, $15,000, accrued in three different jobs) would be reported in INCWAGE.  If, however, a wage-earner worked at a single job during the preceding calendar year, the amounts reported in INCLONGJ and INCWAGE would be the same. 

Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors. 

Values may be negative.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
99999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).

The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="OINCBUS" files="ExtractData" name="OINCBUS" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="321" width="7" EndPos="327"/>
      <labl>Earnings from other work included business self-employment earnings</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[OINCBUS reports net earnings from self-employment in a non-farm business, if this self-employment did not constitute the respondent's longest-held job during the previous calendar year.  The amount earned (in wages, salary, or earnings from self-employment in a business or farm) from the longest-held job during the preceding calendar year is reported in INCLONGJ.     

Imagine that a self-employed individual worked in one non-farm own business for eight months, netting $10,000 in earnings, and worked in two other non-farm own businesses for the remaining 4 months, netting an additional $12,000 in earnings.  The $12,000 in "other" net self-employment earnings (from work outside the person's primary, or longest-held, job) would be reported in OINCBUS; the $10,000 in net earnings from the individual's longest-held job would be reported in INCLONGJ; and the total amount of net self-employed non-farm business earnings from the previous calendar year ($22,000) would be reported in INCBUS.  

Imagine, instead, that as reported in SRCEARN, an individual worked as an employee earning wages for the primary job, but earned additional income working part of the year in their own non-farm businesses.  In such a case, wage income from the primary job would be reported in INCLONGJ; all self-employed non-farm net business earnings would be reported in OINCBUS; and the value of OINCBUS and INCBUS would be the same.   

Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
9999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).


The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="OINCFARM" files="ExtractData" name="OINCFARM" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="328" width="8" EndPos="335"/>
      <labl>Earnings from other work included farm self-employment earnings</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[OINCFARM reports net earnings as a tenant farmer, sharecropper, or operator of one's own farm during the previous calendar year, if such work did not constitute the longest-held job during that period.  The amount earned (in wages, salary, or earnings from self-employment in a business or farm) from the longest-held job during the preceding calendar year is reported in INCLONGJ.     

Imagine that an individual considered raising crops on her own land to be her primary job, and considered money earned by harvesting crops on another farmer's land for a few days, using her own equipment, to be a secondary "own farm" job.  In such a case, net earnings from the sale of  her own crops would be reported as income in INCLONGJ; earnings from harvesting crops for another farmer would be reported as "other" self-employed own farm income in OINCFARM; and the sum of earnings from crop sales and farm equipment rental would constitute INCFARM.  If, instead, she grouped together all net earnings from crop sales and income generated from the use of her equipment into a single "own farm" business, all of this net farm income would be reported in both INCLONGJ and INCFARM, and the value of OINCFARM would be zero.  

Imagine, instead, that as reported in SRCEARN, an individual worked as an employee earning wages for the primary job, but earned additional income working part of the year on their own farm.  In such a case, wage income from the primary job would be reported in INCLONGJ; all self-employed farm net business earnings would be reported in OINCFARM; and the value of OINCFARM and INCFARM would be the same.   

Amounts are expressed as they were reported to the interviewer; users must adjust for inflation using Consumer Price Index [URL omitted from DDI.] adjustment factors.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
99999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).


The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="SRCSURV1" files="ExtractData" name="SRCSURV1" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="336" width="2" EndPos="337"/>
      <labl>First source of survivor benefits</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[SRCSURV1 reports the first source of survivor benefits identified by respondents who reported receiving income from survivor benefits (e.g., from widow's pensions, estates, trusts, annuities, or other survivor benefits except Social Security and VA benefits) during the previous calendar year.  If the individual received survivor benefits from more than one source, the second source of survivor benefits is reported in SRCSURV2.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>06</catValu>
        <labl>Workers compensation pension</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>05</catValu>
        <labl>US railroad retirement survivor pension</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>07</catValu>
        <labl>Black lung survivor pension</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>08</catValu>
        <labl>Regular payments from estates or trusts</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>10</catValu>
        <labl>Other or do not know</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>09</catValu>
        <labl>Regular payments from annuities or paid-up life insurance</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>04</catValu>
        <labl>State or local govt survivor pension</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>00</catValu>
        <labl>NIU</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>01</catValu>
        <labl>Company or union survivor pension</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>02</catValu>
        <labl>Federal government pension</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>03</catValu>
        <labl>US military retirement survivor pension</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="SRCSURV2" files="ExtractData" name="SRCSURV2" intrvl="discrete" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="338" width="2" EndPos="339"/>
      <labl>Second source of survivor benefits</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[SRCSURV2 reports the second source of survivor benefits identified by respondents who answered reported receiving income from survivor benefits (e.g., from widow's pensions, estates, trusts, annuities, or other survivor benefits except Social Security and VA benefits) during the previous calendar year.  The first source of survivor benefits is reported in SRCSURV1.  Individuals who received survivor benefits from only one source are coded as Not in Universe (code 00) in SRCSURV2.]]></txt>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>00</catValu>
        <labl>NIU</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>01</catValu>
        <labl>Company or union survivor pension</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>04</catValu>
        <labl>State or local govt survivor pension</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>02</catValu>
        <labl>Federal government pension</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>03</catValu>
        <labl>US military retirement survivor pension</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>05</catValu>
        <labl>US railroad retirement survivor pension</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>06</catValu>
        <labl>Workers compensation pension</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>08</catValu>
        <labl>Regular payments from estates or trusts</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>07</catValu>
        <labl>Black lung survivor pension</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>09</catValu>
        <labl>Regular payments from annuities or paid-up life insurance</labl>
      </catgry>
      <catgry>
        <catValu>10</catValu>
        <labl>Other or do not know</labl>
      </catgry>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
    <var ID="INCSURV1" files="ExtractData" name="INCSURV1" intrvl="contin" dcml="0">
      <location StartPos="340" width="8" EndPos="347"/>
      <labl>Survivor benefits income from first source</labl>
      <txt><![CDATA[INCSURV1 reports the amount of income from survivor benefits received by a respondent during the previous calendar year, from the source identified in SRCSURV1.  For example, if the source of payments identified in SRCSURV1 were "company or union pension" (code 01), then INCSURV1 would report the amount of income received from survivor benefits from a company or union pension during the previous calendar year.  For persons who reported receiving survivor benefits from a second source in SRCSURV2, INCSURV2 similarly reports the amount of income from survivor benefits received from that second source during the previous calendar year.]]></txt>
      <codInstr><![CDATA[
99999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).


The Census Bureau applies different disclosure avoidance measures across time for individuals with high income in this variable. Detailed explanations of these methods, topcodes, and replacement value and swap value thresholds are available here [URL omitted from DDI.].]]></codInstr>
      <concept vocab="IPUMS">Income Variables -- PERSON</concept>
      <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
    </var>
  </dataDscr>
</codeBook>
